Computer science may well not be a
growth industry going forward.
>> This is Mike Stonbreaker. He's a touring
award winner famous for his fundamental
contributions to database systems like
creating Postgress and more. What was
the hardest part of that?
>> Uh query optimizer. [music] It's just
algorithmically difficult.
>> How do you identify the people who
aren't smart?
>> Well, I mean it's it's very easy.
>> He shared interesting technical takes
from his experience
>> on our benchmarks. large language models
get [music] 0%.
>> Why did you disagree so much with map
produce?
>> That wasn't the only thing Google was
stupid about.
>> I'm curious your thoughts on unsolved
problems in databases and what you think
the future might look like.
Here's the full episode.
The first thing I want to go over is the
story of how Postgress got started. But
for that I kind of want to start at the
beginning. How did you get into building
database systems? When I graduated I had
the good fortune of being hired at
Berkeley
and I it was clear I had to you know
continuing what I did for my PhD was not
going to go anywhere then as well as
today. Uh you're way ahead if you get
adopted by a mentor
who knows the robes. So Gene Wong, who
who is still alive and still
still kicking, uh took me under his wing
and said, "Well, let's do something
together."
And this was 1971,
which was the year after Ted Cod wrote
his pioneering paper in in CACM. Gene
Wong said, "Well, let's let's take a
look at database stuff." And
at the time the the competitors were a
thing called the Kotil proposal which
you're probably too young to have ever
heard of. And so it was a low-level
spaghetti network proposal
uh where you where you executed queries
by following pointers
and then the the alternative was the IBM
proposal which was a hier thing called
IMS which is still available and it's
hierarchical data. It's a tree. You're
organized your data as trees.
And even at the time, IBM realized that
trees were not general enough to to
solve many people's problems.
So they hacked on a a way to make it a
limited network structure.
So it was clear that was a horrible
hack. The Kodasil proposal had all kinds
of bad properties. Uh besides being
low-level and and really hard to debug,
uh it also had the property that if
anything changed in your what's now
called your schema, you basically had to
throw away everything and do it all
again because it was absolutely rooted
of the physical level.
Whereas Ted Cod stuff made perfect
sense. And so Jean said, "Well, let's
build one of these puppies. That's
clearly the the next thing to try."
So we started building Ingress in 1972
while I was an assistant professor at
Berkeley. As you know, if you're an
assistant professor,
you have to you have about you get five
years to prove that you're a big
and they fire you or they give you
tenure. So, Ingress was my ticket to
getting tenure which happened in 1976.
That was where it started. And then
again, you know, happen stance.
Uh, at the time, you know, a lot of
people would build prototypes which were
sort of studenty like code, which means
you could get it to run, but if you gave
it to anybody else, they couldn't.
So we put in the first 90% to get
something we could run and then for
whatever reason we put in the next 90%
to get it to where it really worked.
So the University of California version
of of Ingress was really worked.
And so over the next couple years about
a hundred universities started running
it because Unix became the big thing.
And so this was a database a free
database system that ran on Unix.
And so it was quite popular in in the
academic world. And so we got started
getting you know lots of visitors at
Berkeley who would say gee this is
really nifty looking stuff what's the
biggest biggest day incorous application
you have
and we'd be forced to say not very big
and so this was brought home
uh in spades when Arizona [snorts]
State University
considered running Ingress
on their student records data, all
40,000 students worth.
And they could get over that they had to
get an unsupported operating system from
Bell Labs.
They could also get over they had to uh
run an unsupported op unsupported
database system from these guys at
Berkeley.
But the project went down in flames when
they realized there was no cobalt
available for Unix. and they were a
cobalt shop. So unsupported operating
system, unsupported database system, no
Cobalt doomed us to, you know,
irrelevance.
And it was clear the only way out of
that was to start a company. And so in
1980 uh we got venture capital as it
existed then
and started Ingress Corporation
to move uh Ingress to uh to Dex uh VMS
uh you know a real a real operating
system and we had a real company that
would support Ingress and that was the
start of the commercial journey.
I saw that Ingress was competing with uh
Larry Ellison's offering at Oracle.
>> Yes,
>> I saw that uh Ingress was was certainly
better than what they were offering, but
they were still competing somehow. How
how did they compete?
Uh Larry Ellison is a fabulous salesman
and he at the time he he would he made
present tense and future tense
indistinguishable
and so he basically lied to customers.
He would ship stuff that didn't work
and h have his initial customers help
him debug it. So I think he he he
engaged in what I consider very shady
business practices.
But lying to customers I think is is you
know unconscionable.
So for instance
uh there's a thing called referential
integrity
which is if you I if you fire an
employee
and he's the last person in a given
department do you want to delete the
department or do you want to have it be
a department ghost department? It's it's
all that kind of stuff. And so Ingress
Corporation implemented referential
integrity. Uh Oracle Corporation wrote
two manual pages that said here's the
definition of referential integrity
which everybody agreed to. And then he
then down at the bottom it said not yet
implemented.
[laughter]
>> Interesting. Yeah. I had interviewed
someone who worked at Sun Micros
Systemystems and they had a similar
opinion that they
Larry Ellison was a little bit shady. So
it seems to be a commonality.
Um I also saw somewhere else in
something that you had said was that um
when Oracle acquired my SQL that
everyone kind of got afraid of that and
moved to Postgress. That was the genesis
of Postgress replacing MySQL as the
preferred open-source relational
database system.
So you you created ingress and there was
a lot of technical innovations in it so
that it was better than the the
incumbents but ultimately it it went
away and you developed Postcrest. What
what was the thing that Ingress didn't
do that Postgress would do? Uh the big
thing that guided us at the very
beginning
was the the original reasoning
for
the academic version of Ingress was we
were going to support a geographic
information system that the neighboring
professor Pine Veriah wanted.
And so to support a GIS system, you need
points, lines, polygons, line groups,
that sort of stuff.
And it was clear that Ingress couldn't
do it because the data types we put into
Ingress were the standard ones,
integers, floats, uh, text, strings, and
you couldn't support, you couldn't
efficiently support
uh, GIS types on top of that. So, as a
GIS, the academic version of Incorus was
a complete failure.
And that was in the back of of our mind.
The other thing that happened, this is a
little out of chronic chronological
sequence, but it helps make the point is
that the commercial version of Ingress I
think around
1985.
uh you know there was ANIE had just
proposed
uh a date and time standard for
relational databases
and so uh commercial Ingress implemented
date and time
uh you know using the standard Gregorian
calendar and so I was associated with
the commercial version of Ingress as
well as I was still at the University of
California as a professor so I I got a
call from from an Ingress customer who
said, you know, you implemented date and
time wrong. And I said, huh? We
implemented the Gregorian calendar and
you can subtract
uh and you know if it has, you know,
days have 30 or 31 months except for
February, except for leap years. So
subtraction on dates works exactly the
way you would expect it to.
But he said that's not what I want in
his particular world. He he said he was
he was dealing with with
bond financial instruments and for some
reason I mean you got the same amount of
interest on a on his financial bonds
during each month no matter how long the
month was.
So he had the date you bought the bond,
the date you sold the bond. He wanted to
do a subtraction,
multiply it by the coupon rate, and say
that's what that's the interest we paid
you.
But of course, his version of
subtraction was March 15 minus February
15th is 30 days because that's the
definition of his calendar.
And so he had to uh retrieve two dates
out to user code, do the subtraction in
user code, put the answer back, and it
cost him a factor of two or three in in
efficiency.
And he said, "Why can't I just overload
your definition of subtraction with what
I want?" And of course with Ingress, it
was hardcoded.
And the problem was this is a case where
you wanted bond time just like you
wanted uh points, lines and polygons.
And so Postgress was engineered to have
an extendable type system.
So you could have whatever data types
you wanted and they were very efficient
and that was the main gist of Postgress
was that it had that flexibility.
Uh and as
you know in business data processing
a lot most people were happy with the
standard data types but relational
databases started to spread to all kinds
of other places what are called abstract
data types or you know uh stored
procedures you know bunch of names
they're called uh you know had had great
applicability
and so Postgress that was that was the
big thing in Postgress. Uh we also
Postgress also
uh supported what the AI guys at the
time wanted in the way of inheritance.
Uh we also supported time travel. Uh but
the implementation absolutely sucked and
it got taken out after a while. So there
were a huge number of of really nifty
things at Postgress.
>> You mentioned you you want to hire
extraordinary software engineers and I
think you've you've said before that you
have no trouble finding those people.
How do you identify those people in your
hiring that they're the extraordinary
ones?
It's usually pretty obvious. I mean I
have a good feel for how difficult stuff
is. if they get 3x the am the the amount
done, you know, in school that I think
is reasonable, then then they're
incredible.
>> On the flip side, you had this
interesting quote. I wrote I wrote it
down. He said, um, I can't stand people
who are who aren't really smart. It's
challenging to talk to them. How do you
identify the people who aren't smart?
>> Well, I mean, it's it's very easy. you
you talk to them and and it it rapidly
you can rapidly surface whether they're
smart or not. You know, what was your
master's thesis? What did you do? Uh
well, how did it how did it exactly
work? Well, how did you deal with error
conditions?
Uh [snorts] how many processes did you
have? Why didn't you use threads?
I only you ask them technical deep
technical quest questions.
>> You you gave a talk and I think there's
also a paper behind it of this idea that
uh one sizefits all database systems not
optimal one size actually fits none and
that what you really want is database
solutions that target specific needs.
What database offerings you see today
that are one-sizefits-all? In 2004 when
I wrote the paper, we had an academic
project which was building what became
streambase. And so a stream processing
engine looks nothing like a relational
database.
And we had the gist of an idea for
column stores for the for data
warehouses which was popularized by
Vertica looks nothing like a row store.
So here were three wildly different
implementations that had no resemblance
to each other and in each case they were
an order of magnitude faster than the
other guys. So it's pretty clear that
one side, you know, that in with those
three instances,
you give up an order of magnitude
uh when you're running a database system
that isn't
that isn't architected for your kind of
stuff. I think that's still true. I
mean, I think Clickhouse is a column
store. Pine cone is faster than
userdefined types
on on textbased vector processing.
And so I think it's it's still very much
the case [snorts] and I think
there's no difficulty
putting a common parser on top of
multiple implementations.
uh Postgress has so far chosen not to do
that. they don't implement a column
store
and so I think they are not they are not
competitive you know on sizable data
warehouses
they also don't have multi-node support
again for people with big data
warehouses that's table stakes so I
think it's just as true today as it ever
was I think that
what is true
is that if you want to get going, you
have a database problem,
you know, the answer is choose Postgress
[snorts] and there's a huge programming
community, all kinds of all kinds of,
you know, data type implementations.
it's free uh and you can find Postgress
talent easily and get going
and and so I think it's it's it's a
great choice for lowest common
denominator
and until you're trying to do [snorts] a
million transactions a second it works
just fine until you're trying to support
a pabyte data warehouse it it I say at
the low end it it's absolutely
Absolutely the right one sizefits-all at
the low end it's Postgress at the high
end that's just not true
>> GPUs do they make available some new
opportunities to optimize databases
probably but I think the the big
challenge is that GPUs are
you know sum simd you know single
instruction multi- data and that's
that's the anathema of indexing
And so whenever indexing is the right
answer, they're probably not a good
idea.
And I think uh also you've got to
architect them so that the so that the
bandwidth
so that the bandwidth from storage is is
not not the bottleneck. And so if
they're an add-on to the CPU as often as
not the bus connecting it to the the GPU
to the CPU is a bottleneck.
>> Can you explain why indexing would be
not as effective when there's SIMD?
>> So let's let's say I'm I'm [snorts]
looking for Ryan's
I'm looking for Ryan's salary and I have
a B tree.
So you go to the root of the B tree.
You find you find the divider that has
both sides of Ryan.
You follow the pointer.
That's a memory access for sure. Then
you do it all again and you do this like
three or four times.
So that doesn't parallelize well. So the
answer is indexing doesn't parallelize
well. You mentioned B trees. When you
first implemented
uh that first version of ingress, did
you write all of that by hand? Because I
imagine there's probably not some
existing B tree library or something.
>> Yeah, we wrote the original version of
ingress was all written from scratch.
>> What was the hardest part of that
implementation?
>> Uh query optimizer.
>> And why was that hard?
>> It's tough. It's it's just
algorithmically difficult. It's still if
you ask most any senior database
programmer what's the hardest hardest
part, they'll still say the optimizer.
Map produce came out at some point in
the early 2000s and it kind of took the
data world by storm. People were really
impressed by it. They thought Google
really knows what they're doing. this is
the best thing since sliced bread. But
it seems like when I look at the
literature and what you thought at the
time, you kind of disagreed heavily. Why
did you disagree so much with uh map
produce?
Well, I think
there were a lot of
not very enlightened people who said
Google Google is really smart. They must
know what they're doing and so we'll do
whatever they say. And so they would
they would uh they would engage in
Hadoop or engage with Hadoop. But Hadoop
is ridiculously inefficient. And so uh
at the time,
you know, others, you know, Dave Dwit
and others who who were involved in our
2011 paper, we understood distributed
databases
and understood that you could beat the
heck out of Hadoop.
uh with a distributed database system,
which is basically what that 2011 paper
says.
And of course, it was it's true. And
but that wasn't the only that wasn't the
only thing Google was stupid about.
So Google also
had the opinion that eventual
consistency was the right way to do
concurrency control.
And so that was postulated from on high
by Google all during that same period of
time.
And it it wasn't and all the database
people said, you know, you're out of
your frigin mind because it doesn't it
solves one particular kind of problem
but only and that very rarely occurs in
practice. Why did they pursue eventual
consistency?
>> Okay, well the idea is that you have an
east coast database and a west coast
database and they're replicas. So you
want them to be the same. If you say I'm
going to do a transaction, I'm going to
decrement by one the number of widgets
in the west coast warehouse then I'm
going to with before I commit that
transaction I'm going to update the east
coast warehouse pay pay a message over
and back to update it and then to make
sure everything goes well it takes a it
takes another roundtrip a message to
make sure that both of them actually do
the commit correctly. So it's expensive
to do a distributed commit and it still
is. And so the idea was well you you do
the e you do the west coast update you
decrease the widgets by one you just
send a message asynchronously and not in
a transaction so that eventually the
east coast uh warehouse gets decremented
by one.
So meanwhile,
if you're on the east coast, you you
decrement, you know, food stuffs by one.
You send an asynchronous message.
Eventually, the West Coast gets it and
eventually everything settles out. So if
you're allowed to to go below zero
then what will happen is if the east
coast guy and the west coast guy
simultaneously
sell the last widget
then then eventually
uh the
state of the warehouse will be minus one
and somebody won't get their widget
their widget
and So, uh, if if you're allowed like
Amazon to say usually ships in 24 hours,
then maybe you're can allowed to
oversell, but most enterprises can't do
that. And so eventual consistency just
doesn't work. So, we talked a million
hours ago about referential integrity.
So referential integrity in a sales
system is uh integrity constraint is
stock is greater than minus one and that
fails
with eventual consistency.
And so uh Jeff Dean finally of Google
finally figured that out
and uh when they did Spanner, Spanner
had a conventional transactional system
and so Google comp uh completely
abandoned eventual consistency
and completely abandoned map reduce.
>> So the trade-offs basically um
correctness for performance. So, it's
performance versus data integrity. And
if you don't care about your data,
then you're willing to deal with with
bad things happening.
So, did you ever talk to the Google team
while they were doing those things that
you thought were so wrong? We talked to
them before the
2011 paper
and said, "Why why don't we why don't we
partner up and do some stuff?" And they
weren't they weren't interested.
So, they declined. Have you seen other
examples in other big tech companies
where their databases or database
solutions where you actively disagree
with them? like maybe Amazon or or
Facebook. Well, I gave a talk at Amazon
maybe three years ago
and I told them all the things I thought
they were doing wrong and I think uh
Amazon's problem is that they are
supporting you know
15 different database systems
and that's about 12 too many. So, so I
think they have their own culture and I
told I I said you're supporting too many
database systems
and at this point they haven't chosen to
retire any of them.
>> Why do you say that the 15 should be
three? Well, they're supporting a
graph-based database system, and it's
well understood that a graph-based
database system is almost never the
performant option.
And so, if you want a graph, if you
want, if you like the idea of having a
user interface that deals with nodes and
edges, that's fine. put put a layer on
top of a relational database system that
gives you that user model. And so most
of their database systems, there's some
other of their database systems that
better at what it does than
than it is.
And so so the answer is you should
retire
you should retire any database system
that isn't performant
in in a big enough market to justify the
maintenance. you've uh influenced
industry significantly from academia
and my one thought that I had is what
why not work directly in industry or why
why do you prefer the position of being
in academia and having influence in the
way that you have versus just uh taking
a job at AWS or something like that
being a very you know distinguished
engineer there
uh because that gives you to a boss.
[laughter]
And that gives you company rules, limits
your ability to publish, limits your
ability to go talk at conferences,
uh limits your abil your ability to
go go poke at what what various
competitors are doing that they won't
tell their competitors.
But mostly I really like being in
startups and I and I after the
commercial version of Postgress got
acquired by InformX.
You know I was working part-time for
InformX
which was a 2,000 person company and I
didn't feel like I could make a
difference because it was bureaucratic
and and whatever the president wanted he
got.
So, I think I'm just not cut out for I'm
not cut out for politicking. I don't do
that very well
and I have a hard time interacting with
people I think are dumb and that again.
So, I guess I I I have I have some
problems with with big companies.
>> I I want to talk a little bit about
Debboss. I just thought it was a really
interesting technical model. Can you
explain what the boss is? We started the
academic project in
19 2020 something like that. And the
gist of it was
uh at that point Mate Mate Haria who is
on the faculty at Stanford was also one
of the founders of data bricks was the
original creator of Spark.
And so he said uh
at the time data bricks you know
basically was running people's spark
jobs on the cloud. And so he said at any
given time we might be orchestrating a
million Spark jobs.
And so we have to write a scheduler
that's going to decide who to run next
at scale a million.
And he said there was no we tried all
the all the schedulers written by the OS
folks and they they couldn't they didn't
scale.
So we put all the scheduling data in a
Postgress database and basically a
Postgress application was doing
scheduling and then it sort of clicked
that by and large most everything you do
in an operating system
is managing data at scale
and you should do that using database
technology.
So why don't we just replace at least
the upper half of Linux with a database
system.
So that was the gist of the academic
project and we worked on it at Berkeley
and Stanford
uh in the early early 20s and it was it
was very successful. It clearly it
clearly worked.
And in the process
uh the Stanford folks wrote an extension
to uh JavaScript so that you could
program you need some programming world
that can can talk to your
implementation.
So if you're doing what amounts to a
programming language and you're running
on top of what amounts to an operating
system that is a database,
then the obvious thing to do is put all
your state in the database. And that's
exactly what they did. And so we had an
innovative
programming language model, an
innovative operating system model
and and of course then the idea was well
can we start a company
and so we talked to the VCs
who to a person said
you're you're dreaming if you think
you're going to displace Linux. However,
this programming language stuff is
really nifty. We had what amounted to
extensions to JavaScript
that would allow
any any program to have all of the nice
features of a database system. You know,
stuff was durable. You could have
transactions.
If it failed, you'd fail over. You know,
it was all that nifty stuff.
So we got funded
uh to start a company in 2023
and that was Debboss Incorporated and we
decided that that was the name of the
project since it always been the name of
the project
but we were ba we were basically in the
programming language business and so at
the current time uh deboss has a version
of Typescript a version of Java, version
of Joe, Go,
and a version of Python, which which are
basically seamless. It runs what looks
like vanilla programs. In the world of
the cloud, there's every incentive for
you to structure your your your
application as a workflow.
And so we decided that we would support
a workflow system period.
And so the workflow that that deboss
supports in [snorts] those four
languages is the steps in in a workflow,
the individual
micro apps, whatever you want to call
them, are transactional.
Uh workflows are durable. So that once
you do a step it's not forgotten.
Uh and it's clear that we can make
uh workflows atomic if there was a
market for it which means the whole
workflow would either finish or look
like it never happened. So it has very
very nice properties
and is
a great deal faster and a great deal
easier to use than the competition.
So
the company is selling and innovating in
this area.
And so so the idea is that you want to
make state of your application
persistent when you put it in the
database. uh and then it and then you
figure out how to do it fast.
And I [snorts] think their their
business model as we were talking
earlier is very much get and get leaf
level programmers
interested.
So it's been very much uh you know tell
us leaf level programmer tell us what
you need that we don't have get it
quickly
and convince people to try it and
we've been very very successful with
other with other startups who want to
choose the best thing and we're starting
to be to be successful with the the big
boys. So it's it's an interesting
interesting market and I think the key
thing so far it's
probably twothirds of the customers are
doing agentic AI which means that they
have a large language model surrounded
by a bunch of stuff that that adds more
signal
and so far
Most of Agentic AI is read only,
meaning uh you want to produce a
prediction
for whether Ryan is is going to be a
good customer or not. And so that just
runs some stuff and then produces a new
thing that's given to somebody. So
basically read only which means that uh
you're not you're not actually updating
Ryan's credit rating or and so I think
fairly quickly this the whole world is
going to move to using
you know agents to do read write
applications
and that's going to make that's going to
make them very very databasey
and DeBoss does that stuff really really
well. And so, you know, for instance, if
you want to write an agent or two agents
that move a $100 from my account to your
account.
And so you debit my account, you
increment your account
and these two agents have to agree to
commit
or you have to back everything out,
which is to say the workflow [snorts]
needs to be what I called atomic, which
is it all happens or it looks like it
never happened. And so I think the the
demands on in this market will escalate
with with things with people wanting
stuff to be read, right? And so I think
that that will bode well for the market
and bode well for deboss.
And this this what's being offered in
the market today to application
developers differs from the original
research project where that was actually
swapping out the guts of an operating
system with a database. I see that's I
mean that's really cool. I never
imagined replacing all the state of a of
an operating system with a database.
What's the there there's got to be some
trade-off there.
Well, a file system written on top of a
DBMS is faster than than the Linux file
system. The scheduling engine is
competitive with other scheduling
engines. You can make everything fail
over. So, you get high availability
without having to do anything else. The
answer is there there's really no
downside.
Then why wouldn't Linux
incorporate that and upgrade itself with
this? You hope they would. In other
words, you should you should keep all
the device driver junk down at the
bottom because that's there's a lot of
it and no one wants to do that and
replace everything else with the
database implementation.
Is that something that you've mentioned
to Linux people and what's their typical
reaction
>> back in the academic project when I'd
mentioned that to operating system folks
they would get very very threatened
which is this is the database guys
trying to take over their turf
and I think the programming language
guys ditto you know which is you know
the the the
way to implement the runtime for a
programming environment is with a
database.
>> That's uh that's interesting. I mean, if
it's objectively true, then maybe it
will take over.
>> Well, I mean, it took Java 10 years to
become widely accepted. I just think the
time constant is substantial. I think we
talked a lot about the past of databases
and I'm curious your thoughts on
unsolved problems in databases and what
you think the future might look like.
>> Okay. So I think two different things
that I'd like to talk about. The first
one is
like everyone else
three years ago we started to look at
what were large language models good
for. So, we've been trying to get what's
now called text to SQL
uh to we've been we've been trying to
make it work
on real world databases,
especially real world data warehouses.
So we've been trying the technology
on four different production databases
warehouses
where we've gotten the workload the
actual workload that's run
and
you know from the actual users using the
system
[clears throat] and we've gotten them to
reverse engineer the text that
corresponds to that sequence. So we have
text and SQL for we have four
benchmarks.
>> When you say text to SQL, you mean uh
like a human prompting model or
something like I would just in English
that text would be you know everyone
over four years old. Tell me all the
professors at MIT who won the touring
award. And so an LLM is supposedly good
at that.
And so uh the text to SQL benchmarks
there's a one called spider another one
called bird
and the best LLM systems are pretty good
at those benchmarks you know like 80%
accuracy or better
>> so not superhuman
>> not superhuman but they're pretty good
like you would consider using them a and
you know like current current
leaderboard is something like 85% %
accuracy, which I mean it's getting
there. You say maybe it's not quite
ready for prime time, but it's simply it
certainly
looks looks pretty good.
Well, on our benchmarks,
uh, large language models get 0%. And if
you enhance them with rag and and all
the tricks goes to 10%. And if you give
as a prompt the from clause, in other
words, all the actual tables that need
to be accessed [snorts] and all the
actual join clauses that need to be
joined, then accuracy goes to about 35%.
So the definition of this stuff doesn't
is not ready for prime time and not
going to be for a while, if ever.
So what what's the difference? Uh number
one, data wareh you know LL LLMs are
trained on the pile.
Data warehouse data is not in the pile.
And there's an adage that if you haven't
seen the data a couple times before, you
have no chance of regurgitating it.
That's number one. Uh number two uh
query complexity on spider and bird is
maybe 10 to 20 lines of SQL. Real world
data warehouses it's 100 lines of SQL.
Complexity is bigger.
Number three the schema in spider and
bird is clean.
You know the table names are are mmonic.
The column names are pneummonic and
there's no duplication.
In data warehouses, people have
materialized views all the time. It
means there's redundancy
and and column names are often
underscore
Zuppers blah. And so they're not mmonic.
So that makes it a lot harder. uh and
then they also have idiosyncratic data.
So J term is popular thing at MIT. It's
a one-month term in January.
Not unique to to MIT but not very
popular.
So not in the pile
idiosyncratic data simple queries schema
schema is a mess.
make make it not work. And those are
true of every data warehouse I know of.
And so I think the the technology simply
doesn't work and isn't going to work
anytime soon.
So we've been So what do you do? So well
first of all we published our benchmark.
It's a thing called Beaver, which is an
anonymized
and abstracted version of these four
data warehouses.
And so if you think you're really good
at doing text to SQL, try a real
benchmark, not a fake one.
So number two, uh,
borrowing from what I just said, if you
don't have all the join terms and you
don't have the from clause, you're
toast.
What's more, if you don't break down the
query into simpler pieces, you're toast.
So that says to me that uh you want to
give
your retrieval system simpler pieces
which include the from clause and
include join terms. That's number one.
Uh number two, the minute you want to
talk to two different structured
databases, you know, like your data
warehouse and your CRM system,
then it's pretty clear to me that doing
a structured data join using an LLM is a
bad idea. It's just you're much better
off
you leaving them as tables and doing a
join in SQL.
So our point of view is we are trying
out
turning everything into tables. You
know, we're we're working with the
Department of Transportation in the city
of Munich, Germany,
and they have six people full-time who
are answering citizens
complaints,
queries,
which are of the form, how come I don't
have enough time to cross this
intersection next to my house before the
light turns? All kinds of stuff. How
come the trolley doesn't stop for enough
time for me to get on the trolley? You
know, it's How come the trolley doesn't
come uh more than once an hour? I mean,
it's all this stuff. Their database is
the trolley schedule, that's SQL. The
light sequencing, that's SQL.
The intersections, that's CAD.
the federal
you know country of Germany regulations
of this stuff that's text city of Munich
regulations for this stuff which is text
so you got to join SQL SQL CAD text and
text so our point of view is turn it all
into SQL all into tables and do a join
with what amounts to a query optimizer
So that's what we're working on. I think
other people will have other ideas but I
think it's extremely fertile area
because people really want to do it.
So that's number one. Uh number two we
talked earlier about agentic AI. The
minute this becomes read write it's a
distributed database problem and you
want atomicity
consistency all that stuff. I think a
very interesting area. So that's pretty
much what I what I am what I'm working
on now
>> on that benchmark where it's 0% right
now. What percent is human? Like if you
took someone who really knows SQL, what
would they score like the average human?
So once you disambiguate the the text,
a a knowledgeable SQL user programmer
with the schema will do will will get
very high accuracy.
>> Okay. Like 90% or something at least.
>> Okay. Okay. Wow. It's I'm surprised that
the LM so score so lowly on on this kind
of benchmark. Maybe when this goes out,
someone who works at Anthropic will
reach out to you or something and say,
"Let's
>> I'd love to I'd love to find out because
I mean it's a terrific success story
>> for people who want to deeply understand
databases and they're looking for some
material to study. Is there a book that
you recommend that's a top technical
book to learn databases
>> papers in the literature?"
I think uh Joey Helerstein and I
published a red book what's called the
red book which is called readings and
database systems. It's now
eight years old. I mean I think that
that would be a great set of readings
for eight years ago
and beyond that uh papers
popular papers from the literature. If
you could go back to yourself when you
just graduated, give yourself some
advice knowing what you know today, what
would you say?
>> Back at when I first took the job at
Berkeley and without thinking about it
much, we said, "Let's write a database
system." And we we knew nothing about
databases,
nothing about implementations. We were
not skilled programmers
like Bill Joy. So starting off doing
something that was that crazy
was really pretty crazy.
And and you know you you effort and you
make stuff work and you learn along the
way. And so I think the answer is
think outside the box.
Think crazy thoughts
and try and do them.
And I think
to me it's not at all obvious. The the
better question is if you were starting
out today, what would you major in? Uh
because I think, you know, computer
science may well not be a growth
industry going forward. And I'm not sure
I would recommend 18 year olds to major
in computer science.
I mean, I think health health care and
and the building trades are are are safe
bets and everything else looks much
riskier. Uh, if if you're about to get
your PhD and are trying to decide what
to do,
then I think life is pretty easy. you
know, take take the most prestigious job
you can get
and find a mentor who's willing to help
you
and then pick some area that isn't, you
know, like our our stuff, you know,
which is called Rubicon, is definitely
not going with the flow. So, choose
something that's not that isn't going
with the flow
and try and make it work. Both my wife
and I said, "F follow your passion.
Somehow the money will work out." And I
don't believe that for a minute, but I
think that's what you have to tell your
kids. [laughter]
>> And your grandkids.
>> If you don't believe that, then uh why
do you have to tell them that?
[clears throat]
>> My wife is is a good example. So she has
an she has a master's degree in computer
science, undergraduate degree in
computer science, and she wanted to be a
teacher, you know, you know, K K12
teacher. And her parents said, "You
can't do that. It doesn't pay enough
money."
And so I think and I think she ever
since that time has regretted
that decision. She wasn't passionate
about doing computer science. it was
simply a trade.
And so I think find something you're
passionate about and and you will, you
know, either
you won't starve. You may not make a lot
of money, but I think chances are you'll
be happier than if you do something
you're not passionate about. Because I
think a lot of people I know view their
job as simply a job and life is what
happens between 5:00 pm and 8 am. I
don't feel that way at all. I really
like what I do. Wouldn't matter whether
I made a lot of money or didn't.
>> Awesome. All right. Well, thank you so
much for your time. Really appreciate
it.
>> Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype. So, I'd love
to show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market. So,
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback for me about the show, I'd love
to hear it. Comments on YouTube have led
to guests coming on like Ilia Gregoric
and David Fowler. I wasn't aware of them
until someone dropped a comment. Also,
feedback in the comments helped me learn
to reduce the number of cliffhers in the
intros. So, your comments definitely
make a difference. Please keep letting
me know what you'd like to see more of
in the show, and I'll see you in the
next episode.